so let's look at the solution to our
four- level page table quiz we have 2 to
the 64th bytes of address space we have
2 to the 16th bytes in each page we get
that there are 2 to the
48th pages in our address space for a
flat page table the page table has 2 to
the 48 entries times the size of each
entry is 2 to the 3r so the overall size
is two to the 51st bytes so the answer
is here 51 this is an enormous page
table many many terabytes of page table
now let's see what the four level page
table looks like the page number in this
page table is split across four levels
so the page number is split into four
pieces of 12 bits the easiest way to
figure out how large the overall page
table is is to figure out how many
innermost page tables we have 4 GB worth
of memory is 2 to the 32nd bytes which
is 2 to the 16th pages of this size so
we have two to the 16th pages one
innermost page table has two to the 12
entries so it covers 2 to the 12th pages
to cover 2 to the 16th consecutive Pages
we need 2 to the 4th of these innermost
page tables so now we know that we have
innermost page tables how many page
tables at the next level we need to
point to them well each table at that
entry can also have 2 to the 12th
entries and this is only 2 to the 4th so
we need only one so this is the page
table situation we have the outermost
page table has 2 to the 12th or 496
entries but only one of them the first
one actually has a a page table at the
next level that page table at the next
level also has two to the 12 entries but
only one of them the first one points to
the next level of page table that next
level page table has 16 entries that
point to innermost page tables so
overall the number of these page tables
is one here one here one here and 16 of
these for a total of 19 of them the size
of each of these small page tables is
the number of entries 2 to the 12th
times the size of an entry 2 to the3 so
the size of each one of these is 2 to
the 15th bytes which corresponds to 32
kiloby so overall we have 19 page tables
at various levels Each of which is 32
Koby so the solution here is 19 * 32 so
the final answer is 68 kiloby as you can
see this is only 68 kiloby less than a
megabyte compare that to many many
terabytes of page table for a flat page
table organization this is why all 64bit
x86 processors nowadays use multi-level
page tables of at least three
levels